First of all, I offer my bins to the
divine in you.
[Applause]
Pretty much in all the scriptures
there is a uh very important word,
a word without which
your
penance, your sadhana,
your practices are going to be
incomplete.
So I'm going to cover that word today.
If you can
get the essence of this word
or if I can successfully explain this to
you
and get the point across to you,
your chances of success are going to
increase manifold.
The word is purity.
Whatever you do
on the path of self-realization,
you cannot discount
purity.
What do I mean by the word purity?
Or what do I mean when I say pure?
Does pure mean that you take care of
your
physical purity
or does that mean that you take care of
your mental purity
or moral purity?
All of these put together when combined
create what's called spiritual purity.
It is only in a state of spiritual
purity that you are going to
experience anything
divine.
Without a pure mind,
purity of your discipline,
it is not possible to rise above
intellect.
Until such time that you rise above
intellect,
you are not going to experience your
true nature.
What do I mean by
moral purity
or purity of discipline?
This word purity is probably going to
come
many times today in my lecture.
So be prepared for that.
You may think it's repetition,
but really until you instill purity
in your mind, in your actions, in your
thoughts, and in your speech, you are
not going to experience anything divine.
You may do the hardest of all penences
that there are.
You may do
you may practice severe austerities
that is not going to lead to a divine
experience.
So let us begin with
the concept of purity.
Why is it important at the first place?
Imagine you buy a uh really expensive
mirror.
Let's say you spend $10,000 buying that
The mirror is exquisite.
It renders images perfectly.
Now envision that you'll cover that
mirror with uh
some covering bit of dust
of uh clothes of something that makes
the mirror opaque
that covers the mirror so that it is no
longer able to show your own image in
it.
Think about it for a moment. You have
the most expensive mirror
but it is not solving the purpose
because it is unable to render the
images
and
same is the state of your mind.
Unless you have a pure mind
you cannot really attain that supreme
state of meditation.
The thing that is called samadhi or
trans or meditational eupo or tranco or
yogic trans cannot be experienced till
such time that you have a pure mind.
So you may have the finest body, you may
have a really fine brain,
a very sharp intellect.
However,
until
your mind is pure,
you are not going to experience anything
divine, anything profound.
You will continue to uh
understand, assimilate, and assess and
make sense of everything through the
mind. The goal is to rise above the
mind.
[Applause]
So to get to that
there are many steps Patanjali describes
in his epherisms.
They are yama, nyama, asa.
The first three form the basis of first
is moral purity.
It talks about you know things like
non-stealing and nonviolence and
truthfulness and celibacy and stuff like
that. They contribute to moral purity of
a person.
The second part which is nyma the second
kind of rung of the letter
talks about what we call mental purity.
So it talks about you know how you need
to spend time studying various
scriptures and uh things like that.
The third is asa.
Asas or physical postures are designed
for physical purity.
The more you gain that purified state of
the body of your nervous system or more
importantly central nervous system,
the more
you're ready to develop concentration.
The fourth is pranayyama
which is regulation of the breath which
is basically in a way purifying the
vehicle of meditation or concentration
because unless there is breath in you
how are you going to meditate? How are
you going to concentrate?
Then he talks about a concept called
pratahara.
It means withdrawal of senses.
Now that
is spiritual purity. You cannot withdraw
your senses from contemplating on
material objects
until you have purified yourself at the
four levels.
So that discipline of
that purity of discipline is the key.
Until you stick to your discipline and
do so in a qualitative fashion,
you are not going to experience any
purity.
Imagine
a glass of water.
The water in the glass is salty
[Applause]
and your job is to make it pure.
Your job is to
is to purify the water. Your job is to
make it taste like it used to be.
Now you have a couple of options to do
that. One is you keep pouring fresh
water in the in in that uh glass and
there's going to be a time when there
will be no salty water left in the
glass.
When that happens, you would have
purified the water at that point in
time.
But
how about evaporating?
How about the process of distillation?
Could that remove impurities? The answer
is yes.
However,
it is clear that until you really in a
disciplined fashion
do the practice of purifying the water,
the water is not going to be purified.
You can have a glass full of water in
front of you and you can chant all the
mantras on the planet that talks about
purification of the water. You can read
all the texts, all the scriptures, but
that is not going to purify the water,
is it?
And that's exactly what I'm getting at.
Till such time that you stick to your
discipline, you have the purity of
discipline,
the discipline in itself is incomplete,
inadequate, insufficient
and is not going to cut it.
So you really have to have the purity of
discipline of moral discipline, of
intellectual discipline, purity of
physical discipline, purity of spiritual
discipline. It is when you
are going to live in that purity,
breathe that purity, think that purity
and drink that purity that you are going
to experience the real nature of yogic
practice practices. Whether you are a
bakta that is a uh a devotional person
or if you are a yogi
or somebody aspiring to be a yogi in
either case
you must stick to the practice
basically unconditionally.
You must stick to the practice with
utmost purity
and you will see the results very
quickly if you do that.
If you're going to stay impure,
if you're going to just do the things
because you have to do them or because
somebody's asked you to do them but not
really do them with purity.
You are not going to feel any of the
things yogic texts state.
And that's something to remember
forever. forever. That is
imagine
a piece of cloth
that is soiled, it is solid and it is no
longer clean.
Can you clean
let's say a crystal bowl
with that unclean cloth?
The cloth is oiled and soiled.
Can you clean it?
Chances are if you are going to start
cleaning that that crystal bowl with
that
cloth,
you're going to actually make it more
dirty.
And that's what I mean.
If you are going to attempt even try
cleansing your mind or your soul
with
views or with processes or with
discipline that is not pure at the first
place,
how on earth can you expect to perform
the cleansing?
And if you don't
from the cleansing,
how are you going to experience your
true nature?
The mirror that is unclean,
the mirror that is now covered with dust
needs to be cleaned.
Your true nature is hiding behind
the dirt.
It is hiding behind the dirt of your
attachments, your desires, your
expectations, your bad karma, even your
good karma.
It is hiding behind your uh anger
and all those emotions.
Until you perform the cleansing
exercise,
you are not going to see your true
nature.
And that's something you need to
remember.
And that's something you need to work
towards. So what do I mean by moral
purification?
You see morality is the basis of all
virtues. Morality is the key. Morality
is the foundation, the mother of all
virtues.
A moral life
always without exceptions
results in peace.
Deep in your heart,
deep in your conscience,
you always know moral from immoral.
Right or wrong may be subjective,
but moral or immoral are not.
So whether that is practicing
nonviolence, truth,
non-stealing and um things like that
I am going to elaborate on these some
other day uh when we talk about in
detail the yogras of Patanjali his
epherisms. Uh but for now I just want to
stay focused on the topic of purity and
the concept of purity. So moral purity
is when you imbue and instill morality
in absolutely everything you do.
When you morally purify yourself
and when you physically start to live a
clean life,
you would
start to move towards spiritual
purification.
But somewhere in between these two come
the concept of mental purification.
Right now I'm reminded of a uh verse
from uh Bhagat Gita.
Krishna says to Arjuna that after
reading so much of literature from
various sources you stand deluded my
friend. Krishna says to Arjuna that you
stand confused
and because your your mind is deluded
that's why the world is attracting you
that that's why the illusurary nature of
the world is still attractive to you.
But once you are firmly established in
the practice of yoga, Krishna says, you
will no longer
feel these things.
You will start to see your true nature
and you will no longer be deluded or
illusioned about the reality of things.
So mental purification is about you have
intellectually absorbed
a lot of things that is that are
borrowed
from sources that are not authentic
from people who haven't had firsthand
experience.
Never ever underestimate the power of
direct experience.
So you have accumulated knowledge from
those who did not pass it on based on
experiential knowledge but did so based
on secondhand knowledge. They read it
somewhere. They heard it from somewhere
and they passed it on to you and you
accepted it
or you analyzed it but not in detail
because till your mind is steady you
cannot do analysis. Simple as that.
You can say whatever you like but the
fact is till your mind is steady still
and settled and stabilized and pacified
and calm it is not possible to carry out
deep analysis into anything at all.
So mental purification is about
unlearning. Mental purification is about
getting rid of all the rubbish that you
have acquired
over years.
Believe it or not, it is a very
important aspect of yogic practices.
Unlearning.
I spend a great deal of my time on
learning a lot that I knew.
Imagine you
belong to Australia. Imagine you're an
Australian.
You drive on the left side of the road
and you move to America.
There they drive on the right side of
the road.
Now you have to get your driver's
license in the US.
I hope you agree that in order in kind
of in order to get your license in the
states, you have to unlearn some of the
ways you learned in Australia. You
learned in Australia that driving on the
left is the way to go. You learned in
Australia that giving way to the traffic
from the right on a roundabout is what
you need to do. But is exactly the
opposite in the states.
to correctly learn the ways of the
states, you have to unlearn the ways of
Australia.
So the same goes for yogic practices,
the same goes for
uh for many things that you would
encounter on the path of
self-realization. There are things you
have to unlearn.
And when you unlearn, your mind becomes
ready to learn something new.
I'm reminded of a u little story.
There was a u guy
very well read.
He was a uh PhD
a professor
in a uh state university.
He hears about this monk who had uh
recently come to the town.
He heard that the monk has uh some
wonderful things to offer and direct
experiential knowledge.
So one fine day he decides to go to the
monk.
He goes there and uh
with complete disregard to the basic
mannerisms of
how you approach uh somebody you want to
learn from. Certainly from the eastern
point of view,
he just goes there, takes his seat and
says, you know, please give me some
knowledge. Give me some uh jana, he
says. The monk says, oh, sure. What is
the rush? He says,
why don't you have a cup of tea first?
He goes. Professor, oh yeah, I surely
would like a cup of tea.
So the monk makes tea for the professor.
He gives professor a cup, an empty cup,
and starts pouring in the tea.
And he keeps on pouring.
And the cup is full now. But he keeps on
pouring. The cup starts to overflow.
The tea, the hot tea, I should say,
starts to overflow and gets onto the
hands of the professor who's holding the
cup. and he shouts out loud saying, "Oh
my god, can't you see the cup is full?
There's you cannot fit any more tea in
there. I'm done. Thank you very much. I
don't want more tea."
And the monk goes, "That's exactly what
I want you to know. If you are going to
come full, how can I give you anymore?"
So, first empty yourself of the
preconceived notions you have, of the
perceptions you have,
of all the rubbish you have in your head
about who you are and what all you know.
Clear yourself of those first and then
come back to me and I will give you
knowledge. Right now, you're so full,
you have no space, no place left for
knowledge.
So mental purification is about clearing
up and cleansing your mind
from all the silly things
you have learned over the years from
halfcooked
sources, halfpaked knowledge
that you have not put to experience.
Knowledge you have not validated or
authenticated or verified.
knowledge you have just accepted.
When you are done reading or when you
are done gratifying your intellect,
that is the time you are ready for
meditation. That is the time when you
are ready for self-discovery.
Let's say you set a discipline. I am
going to meditate an hour a day no
matter what.
Some days maybe you need to take a
break. Okay, that is part of the
discipline.
But when you start to say to yourself,
you know what, today I'm very very
tired, so let me skip my meditation
today. You have just
made your discipline impure.
And if you sit down for an hour and you
don't feel like meditating, but you
said, you know what, I'm just going to
sit down anyway. Once again, that is not
purification. That is not purity of the
discipline. So the purity of the
physical discipline is going to be sit
in the poster. You have to sit sit at
the time you have to sit meditate when
you have committed when you have made a
resolution that I'm going to meditate at
this time of the day.
Your mental purification at that point
in time is actually meditating.
Your mind is distracted. It's running in
all the different directions.
Keeping it to continue to bring it back
to the object of meditation is what you
need to do.
So at that point in time it does not
matter
what you want.
That's what you have to do and that's
what you got to do if you want results.
[Applause]
So quality very key.
Now you you decide you're going to spend
some time self analyzing or you know
self inquiry as it's called you have to
do it
whether the path is easy or hard
whether it is straight or windy.
It can be as zigzag
as anything.
The fact is until you tread it, you're
not going to enjoy the journey.
And I'm just requesting you
to
stay away from an intellectual journey
because that will take you away
from the path of self-realization
that is not going to get you to
self-realization. that is going to move
you away far far away away from
self-realization,
self- purification,
self analysis,
self-discovery
and self-realization.
This is how it moves. You work on your
purification
with a calm mind now or calmer mind I
should say. You will be ready to analyze
yourself. Consequently, stabilize
yourself and discover yourself and then
realize yourself
and then
all of this can stop. Imagine a student
who is uh in grade six in the school and
he uh
passes the grades with uh with uh flying
colors.
He no longer needs the books of the
previous class he's just graduated from,
does he?
So once you have gotten yourself to a
certain level,
a lot of things will cease to matter for
you.
[Applause]
And that's what self-realization is
about. When you are no longer dependent
on anything external at all. When you're
no longer dependent on people, on
circumstances, on things, on
achievements, on attainments, for
happiness, on lack of it,
you are self-realized.
And when you can stay in that state no
matter what, all the time, every moment
of your life, you are self-realized.
When the only thing you give out is
love, you are self-realized.
When the only thing that you can do
under all circumstances,
disagreeable circumstances, I mean when
the only thing you do is forgive, you
are self-realized
because these are the signs of
self-realized person. They have uh
limitless compassion, generosity,
forgiveness.
Because when you are self-realized,
you come to understand that this is what
life is about.
You the naturally what you feel for
everybody is compassion.
Anybody's pain is as painful as uh will
cause you as much agony and grief as to
the person who actually has it.
That is self-realization. Because why?
You start to see everybody in you and
you in everybody. I'm not talking about
the physical body. I'm talking about the
purest form of your soul. Something we
may call self or soul.
And that is all you got to remember.
So in summary, purification,
mental purification, physical
purification, intellectual purification,
moral purification will lead to your
self- purification. When you stand self-
purified, you are ready to do self
analysis. That will lead you to the path
of self-discovery and that will take you
further to the path of self-realization.
This is the way to go, my friend. If you
liked what I said, you are free to keep
it. Else you're free to just uh discard
it. Thank you very much. That's all I
have for you today.
[Applause]
Hurry, hurry, hurry, hurry.
Hurry, hurry.
[Music]
[Applause]